<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
	<title>mat383.com</title>
	<link>https://mat383.com/blog/</link>
	<description>Blog posts from in Blog mat383.com</description>
	<ttl>60</ttl>
	<generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
	<language>en-us</language>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2024 04:23:38 +1000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://mat383.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	
	
	<item>
		<title>Building this website</title>
		<link>https://mat383.com/blog/building-this-website/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2024 04:23:38 +1000</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://mat383.com/blog/building-this-website/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLDR:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;I wanted to get into game development and have a website with a shiny custom domain to blog on. I built it with Hugo and it&amp;rsquo;s being hosted on Cloudflare Pages with a Cloudflare domain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-why&#34;&gt;The why&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So just like the next guy, I&amp;rsquo;ve always had an interest in creating games, programming, and making cool stuff. I just never had the motivation or patience to learn to do those things to a standard that I could be proud of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About two years ago, I was inspired by some great story-based games I played at the time and had an idea for a game. No, it was more of a hazy vision. It was an ambitious story-based game of my own that I knew I had to make. The thought of playing that game and sharing it with the world captivated me. I started making notes of ideas I had relating to this game and was obsessively thinking about it for months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But eventually, I came to the realization that this project was way too ambitious for me to do in a couple short years, especially with my lack of experience with proper game development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;ll go get some!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone in the indie game dev community says it&amp;rsquo;s a common mistake for newbies to make their big dream game the first project they work on. They also say you should have an online presence &lt;em&gt;while&lt;/em&gt; making your games, otherwise you&amp;rsquo;ll be swallowed by the sea of everyone else&amp;rsquo;s indie games. Those both sounded like valid bits of advice so I thought I should spin up a website, start making small games, and document their development online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Why a website though? Can&amp;rsquo;t you just make a YouTube channel like everyone else does?&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten tired of editing videos. I also didn&amp;rsquo;t find much interest in other people&amp;rsquo;s dev logs on the platform at the time. Writing text-form posts on a website also sounded like a way more convenient way of sharing updates. However, I admit that it would be nigh impossible to get new eyeballs on me without a presence on YouTube, so I will make some posts into videos when I get a good editing workflow going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;early-attempts-bad&#34;&gt;Early attempts (bad)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started building the website when my ambition greatly outweighed my rusty HTML/CSS skills, Like, massively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I whipped up this concept in Photoshop. The idea was that the entire website would be themed to resemble the profile picture I use everywhere. Heaps of slow-moving PNGs of soft green circles would make up the background and everything would have graceful animations. It was a neat idea, but if you&amp;rsquo;re familiar with the concept of colour banding and why it ruins gradients, you&amp;rsquo;d know why this would&amp;rsquo;ve been horrible in practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mat383.com/images/old-mat383-website-concept.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A very old concept of mat383.com&#34; width=&#34;550&#34;/&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;figcaption&#34;&gt;graphic design is my passion&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I tried to make that website myself. I never built an entire website before though so I jumped head first into writing static HTML by hand, giving zero thought to how the blog will actually blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah don&amp;rsquo;t do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mat383.com/images/old-mat383-website-prototype.png&#34; alt=&#34;A very old prototype of mat383.com&#34; width=&#34;750&#34;/&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;figcaption&#34;&gt;Well, there&#39;s some resemblance&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I even tried making that cool animated background I was talking about. I didn&amp;rsquo;t know any Javascript at the time though so I called upon ChatGPT to do it all for me. We really tried, there was a lot of back and forth. The furthest we got is spreading a bunch of PNGs across the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mat383.com/images/old-mat383-website-bg-prototype.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;An old work-in-progress background for mat383.com&#34; width=&#34;750&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can download these scuffed prototypes &lt;a href=&#34;https://mat383.com/files/mat383.com-prototypes.zip&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came to my senses after all that and stopped trying to make the website like this. I think I dropped the project for about half a year after that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;whats-a-web-framework&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s a web framework??&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A while later, I started over from scratch. This time, I&amp;rsquo;d make the website&amp;rsquo;s backend before the front-end. I did some research on how I could make a blog with Python, the language I was the least inexperienced with. Django seemed like a pretty popular pick, so I looked up some tutorials on how I could do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went through several tutorials but they were all so fast that I didn&amp;rsquo;t understand what the code I was copying did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mat383.com/images/old-mat383-website-prototype-2.png&#34; alt=&#34;An old prototype of mat383.com&#34; width=&#34;650&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not giving download links for these, I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure I put my personal password in one of their databases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gave up again for a while, then I stumbled upon &lt;a href=&#34;https://landchad.net&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;landchad.net&lt;/a&gt;, a website that has a simple tutorial on how to set up a very basic web server. I decided to follow it and bought the domain &lt;a href=&#34;https://mat383.com/&#34;&gt;mat383.com&lt;/a&gt; from Cloudflare and rented a VPS from Vultr. I bought the domain from Cloudflare because I was convinced they had the cheapest prices and least amount of upselling BS (it was honestly impressive after browsing the sites of other domain name registrars). I chose Vultr for my hosting because that&amp;rsquo;s what the website recommended, but I&amp;rsquo;d advise against using them now (their support is bad, but more on that later).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After doing their tutorial, I had my very own website!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mat383.com/images/barebones-mat383-website.png&#34; alt=&#34;Barebones mat383.com&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;/&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;figcaption&#34;&gt;It IS a website...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was only three lines of text, but I had a web server running with a domain. That was cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to try using Django again, but properly. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLlM3i4cwc8zBRQOGXuLrCLNfpVOuVLuwZ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;This course&lt;/a&gt; on YouTube was very thorough, way more thorough than the other tutorials I did in the past, but I also had a lot of issues with it. Sometimes they would skip over small details or my configuration would be different to theirs so I spent way more time troubleshooting than following their instructions. It took me almost a month to complete the roughly hour-long course, as I got tired from troubleshooting and took breaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mat383.com/images/simple-mat383-website.png&#34; alt=&#34;Barebones mat383.com&#34; width=&#34;600&#34;/&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;figcaption&#34;&gt;Not much changed&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I remembered that course was only for setting up the production workflow of a Django website, I still had to make the website after all that!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;enter-hugo&#34;&gt;Enter Hugo&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as I was about to embark on a quest to finally learn Django again, I learnt about the existence of &lt;em style=&#34;font-family:serif; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;static site generators&lt;/em&gt;. They are tools that let you build entire static websites using a bunch of well-formatted templates and content files. Since they&amp;rsquo;re static and lightweight, some places like Github and Cloudflare will even let you host them for free! The lack of a backend makes static websites much faster than typical dynamic websites, but they also can&amp;rsquo;t have any server-side logic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose Hugo as my static site generator as I&amp;rsquo;ve heard of it before and it didn&amp;rsquo;t seem to hard to learn. Setting it up was much simpler than all the stuff I did with Django. I watched &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZFL09qhKi5I&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;this YouTube video&lt;/a&gt; that explained the basics of Hugo and provided &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/LukeSmithxyz/lugo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;a basic theme&lt;/a&gt; for me to use. I modified the theme, some of the templates, and the CSS until I was happy how it functioned and looked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mat383.com/images/recent-ish-mat383-website.png&#34; alt=&#34;mat383.com built with Hugo&#34; width=&#34;700&#34;/&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;figcaption&#34;&gt;An earlier version of this site built with Hugo&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mat383.com/images/almost-done-mat383-website.png&#34; alt=&#34;mat383.com built with Hugo, almost finished&#34; width=&#34;700&#34;/&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;figcaption&#34;&gt;The home page at the time of writing&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not completely finished yet, but I&amp;rsquo;m quite happy with this website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also moved my website off Vultr and onto Cloudflare Pages. I won&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about forgetting to pay for hosting there because it&amp;rsquo;s free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT:&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;rsquo;m going to be moving away from Cloudflare entirely soon. While I don&amp;rsquo;t consider myself a privacy enthusiast (you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t need to be an &amp;ldquo;enthusiast&amp;rdquo; to care about your privacy), I want to respect those who do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;ok-what-now&#34;&gt;Ok, what now?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I start developing games, I want to polish up this website and add a couple features. Adding comment support to this website is my number one priority right now, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to finish it in time (I just &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to write this post on the third day of the eighth month).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d also like to join a couple website collections and webrings. I specifically designed this website to be very lightweight so I can get into the &lt;a href=&#34;https://512kb.club/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;512KB Club&lt;/a&gt;. You see, I grew up using a terrible internet connection (5Mbps down, 1Mbps up) with a low-end laptop. I understand why making lightweight software is important. The homepage of my website currently weighs in at about &lt;strong&gt;40KB&lt;/strong&gt;, so I should be able to get into the &lt;em class=&#34;green&#34;&gt;Green Team&lt;/em&gt; of the 512KB Club and I can put a neat little green badge in the footer. &lt;em&gt;Yippeeee!!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	</channel>
</rss>
